hello everyone
welcome to an introduction to object
oriented programming
in this course
we will be getting into what
object-oriented programming means
as well as going over its four main
principles
this course will assume that you have
some knowledge of programming before
hopping in
if that's not the case
i would suggest checking out our
introduction to programming video which
will be linked in the description
that video will give you information on
the basics of programming that are
necessary to be able to understand more
advanced topics such as those covered in
this video
for this lecture
we will be exploring object oriented
programming in a manner that will be
applicable for its use in any
programming language in which it is
supported
examples will be used to explain the
concept being discussed
however they will be explained well
enough that specific knowledge of the
language being used in the example will
not be necessary
with that being said let's get into it
in this first section
we will be going over what object
oriented programming actually is
in order to understand what
object-oriented programming is
it's best to first understand what
objects are
and in order to do that
it's best to first understand what
primitive data types are
so let's start there
primitive data types are exactly what
they sound like
variables that store single simple
values
examples of such primitive types are the
byte
int
float
double boolean and char
these primitive types only act to store
a single piece of data of a certain kind
and for a while when programming was
still developing this was just fine many
programs being written at the time
weren't complex by today's standards
thus programmers could get away with
only using these primitive types
however
as programs became larger and more
complex primitive data types weren't
really cutting it anymore
programmers began to want to group
variables of similar type together
why would this be useful
well to serve as an example let's
imagine you are trying to program a
chess game when programming a knight
into the game there are plenty of
variables that you will need in order
for the piece to work how it should
for example
you would need a position variable to
keep track of where the knight is
additionally
you would need a boolean to represent
whether the piece has been captured or
not
because if it has
you would not want it to show up
nor should you be able to move with it
you may also need a variable to
represent which color the knight is
so that the game can treat it correctly
these are just a few of the variables
that you would need for one piece
and you would need one of each of these
variables for each piece on the board
each of which would contain different
data
clearly it would be easiest if you could
group all of the variables related to
say one of your knights together
so that you may deal with them as one
entity
additionally
you may want to group your two knights
together as they behave similarly
you then may want to group the pieces of
each side together as they would be
treated differently in reference to each
other
in essence grouping related variables
together is almost necessary when it
comes to complex programs
this is where the struct or structure
came in
in c
the structure is similar to an array
if you don't know what an array is i'd
suggest you check out either our
introduction to programming course for
an overview
or our data structure series for a more
in-depth look at both arrays and many
other data structures
both arrays and structures allow the
programmer to store several pieces of
data together
however structures vary from arrays in
that structures allow the programmer to
store data of different types together
for instance whereas an array would
allow you to store only ins or only
strings
using a structure you could store ins
and strings together along with other
data types
a structure can even store other
structures within it
a structure can be very useful in the
earlier chess example because you could
store all of the useful pieces of data
related to the knight in one structure
that represents that knight
you could then store your knight
structures together in one structure
that represents all of the knights and
so on
the structure allowed such grouping to
take place beyond what arrays were
capable of
the structure is in many ways the
precursor to the object which of course
object oriented programming is oriented
around
the main issue with using a structure in
this way
and an issue that objects would come to
remedy
was that you could not define functions
within a structure you could only
reference them
when object-oriented programming came
along
objects allowed you to store data of all
kinds together and additionally define
and store functions
now before we go much further i should
get into exactly what objects are
objects are instances of a class
and a class is basically a template for
an object
this may seem like a circular way of
looking at these concepts but allow me
to explain
let's say i define a night class
in this class i would define and store
data that is common of all knights
this would be mainly the way that
knights are able to move
thus in this class i would define a
function that uses the knight's current
position to return squares that the
knight can move to
i may also define a position variable
as well as a color variable but i would
not initialize them
when it comes to specific things such as
variables that each object under the
class
in this case each night would have
different data for it's best to define
them when i create the object rather
than in the class itself
for instance each of the four knights
that begin in a game of chess start on
different squares than one another
initializing the position variable in
the night class would imply that you
want each knight object created from
this class to begin with the same
position which you do not
however
each of the knights would behave the
same in terms of the squares it could
move to based on their position
and thus it is best to define a move
function in the class rather than
repeating the same function definition
in each object that i create
when creating a night object you
initialize its attributes or its
variables
and its methods or its functions to
contain information specific to that
night
whereas the night class represents any
given night
a night object represents one night in
particular
essentially object-oriented programming
is the best tool us programmers have
right now to create complex programs by
grouping together related data and
functions
throughout the course of this video we
are going to be getting into detail into
how all of this works using the four
main principles of object-oriented
programming those being encapsulation
abstraction
inheritance and polymorphism
this next section is going to be
focusing on the first of the four main
principles of object-oriented
programming
encapsulation
encapsulation refers to bundling data
along with methods that can operate on
that data within a class
essentially it is the idea of hiding
data within a class that anything
outside that class cannot directly
interact with
that is not to say that they are unable
to interact with the separate object's
attributes at all however
instead
members of other classes looking to
interact with the attributes of an
object should only be able to do so
through that class's methods
in practice
one way this tends to work is by
creating getting and setting methods
these methods act to either get
information from an object or set
attributes to different values
for instance
think back to the chess example from the
previous section
if i was moving one piece and i wanted
to determine whether it was able to
capture another piece
i would need to define a dot get method
associated with each piece that returns
the piece's color in this case piece dot
get color
this way
i could check the color of any piece
from anywhere in my code without having
to access the internal attributes of
said pieces
this allows us to retrieve the
information from where it is defined
additionally
this makes it easiest to keep track of
attributes that depend on one another
for example
if i was programming a game
i may have two different attributes for
the player's health
maxhealth and current health
when the character levels up
i may have their max health increase as
well
when this happens
i would want the current health to be
set to the maximum health
instead of changing both of these values
directly
i can define the set max health method
such that the current health is also set
to the maximum health once the maximum
health has increased
furthermore
these setting methods allow values to be
validated
for instance
if current health is not able to exceed
maximum health
then i would have the set current health
method check if current health would be
greater to maximum health before making
the change
finally you may want some values to be
read only from outside a class
which means you would only define a
getter method and not a center method
for another example
let's look back at chess
when dealing with a piece's position
you would want to keep track of its rank
or its row
and its file or its column
when the piece moves you may think it
would be okay to just set piece.rank and
piece.file to new values
however
as discussed above
this is not the best way to handle it
it would be better to define a ps.move
function that takes the intended new
position and checks if that is indeed a
valid move
the piece would not be able to move if
say the new location is off the board
a piece of the same color is already on
that square
or making such a move would put the king
of the same color in check
additionally
other methods may be called from this
move method for instance one that
captures an enemy piece if it was on
that square
or one that puts the enemy king in check
were the pieces attributes just to be
directly changed
you could end up in a strange situation
where illegal moves are played and
pieces occupy the same square
essentially
getter methods allowing validation can
be very useful
encapsulation is useful for a variety of
reasons
as we just went over it is best to not
allow anything external to directly edit
an object's attributes
this is especially true when working on
large and complex programs where you may
want individual pieces of the program to
work well without requiring them to rely
on every other section of the code
in this way
preventing each piece of your code from
referencing and requiring knowledge of
the inner workings of each other section
of code is very important to keep your
program from becoming completely
entangled in itself
this is an idea we will touch upon in
future sections to come
but for now it's best to understand that
information hiding that is keeping one
class from being able to directly access
the data of another class
is important to keep control of your
program and reducing its overall
complexity
overall
encapsulation is a vital component of
object-oriented programming that allows
the programmer to maintain control of
their data
and to keep their program from ending up
in any unwanted states
in this next section we are going to be
discussing the next of the four main
principles of object-oriented
programming abstraction
abstraction refers to the idea of only
showing essential details and hiding
everything else
this idea is present in everyday life
when you drive your car there are some
things you need to understand about
you need to understand how the steering
wheel steers the car and how the gas and
brake pedals work
you also need to know how much gas your
car has and that it needs gas to work
these are necessary details for you to
be able to drive the car properly
however the exact way that the car works
internally isn't something that most
people need to concern themselves with
how the gas reacts in the engine and how
that translates into the car moving
forward really isn't important while you
are driving your car
all that matters is that you know it
will work this way
whoever built the car had to worry about
how exactly the car would work so that
you don't have to
this idea extends to object-oriented
programming
the classes you create should act like
your car
users of your classes should not worry
about the exact inner details of said
classes
this idea is similar to that of
encapsulation that we discussed in the
previous section
earlier we mentioned how you should not
have classes directly interact with the
data stored within other classes
rather have them use the classes methods
to access their data
this idea is especially important when
you want to work on your program
incrementally where you focus on one
class at a time
and ensure that it works
this is a very useful approach as it can
be difficult for you to focus in the big
picture while programming and splitting
up your project into smaller chunks can
make it much more manageable
furthermore
programs nowadays are vast and complex
to the point where multiple programmers
tend to work on one project
in this case
it's best if the section that you are
working on is able to function without
knowledge of the inner workings of your
colleague section
to achieve this it's best to think of
your program in terms of interface and
implementation the interface refers to
the ways that sections of code are able
to communicate with one another
this is typically done through methods
that each class is able to access
the exact implementation of these
methods or how the methods are coded
should be hidden within the class and
not accessible from the outside
think of this like the car
the other classes are able to turn the
wheel and push the gas
and they know what the outcome should be
without caring about exactly how this
gets done
let's return to the chess example that
we've been using throughout the video
let's say that you are working on making
the night work as it should and a fellow
programmer is working in the king class
in order to effectively work together
you need to agree on an interface with
which these pieces are able to
communicate
in this case
say that you are working on making the
knight unable to move if your king is in
check
as the programmer of the night class
you make the knight use the king's
getter method that will let the knight
know whether or not the king is in check
if it is
then you make it so the knight is not
able to move unless it is able to put
the king out of check
as you program the night class you
should not be concerned with how the
king is determining whether or not it is
in check
the king's method that tells the knight
whether or not it is in check is part of
the interface
but how exactly it does that is part of
the implementation
this manner of only allowing the classes
to interact through a predetermined
interface
prevents different pieces of the program
from becoming completely coupled
together
if the night class has to look into the
king class in order to make a
determination
then it is reliant on the king class
being set up in a certain way in order
to function
if the king clash is changed or
reorganized or its data is renamed
then the night class would no longer
work and it too would have to be changed
assuming the rest of the program was
coded in this way
then many other classes would also have
to be modified
creating a set interface through which
classes can interact with one another
ensures that each individual piece can
be changed without creating a ripple
effect that causes the entire program to
have the change in response
overall it's best to keep in mind
abstraction when writing object oriented
code
as it allows the program to be worked on
incrementally and prevents it from
becoming completely entangled in itself
and very complex
determine specific points of contact
that can act as the interface between
classes
and only worry about the implementation
behind it when working on that section
this next section will be tackling
inheritance
the third of the main principles of
object oriented programming
inheritance is the principle that allows
you to derive classes from other classes
classes can inherit certain methods and
attributes from another class
we will get into exactly what this means
in a moment but first let's look at an
example
let's say you are programming a game
in this game the player has access to
weapons to fight their enemies
to begin you may establish a weapons
class this class would contain many of
the pertinent attributes and methods
common to weapons
for instance an attribute that
represents the damage that the weapon
deals
and a method that deals damage to an
opponent when called
you then would want some more classes to
represent specific weapons such as a
sword or a club
these classes would act differently from
one another as swords and clubs have
certain different attributes such as a
sword being made for cutting
whereas a club is blunt
these differences would be represented
in different values for their attributes
as well as possibly different attributes
altogether
however
they do share much of the same behavior
as they are both members of the weapons
class
in this case
the weapon class would be the superclass
and the sword and club classes that
extend the weapon class would be
subclasses in relation to it
many of the attributes and methods
associated with the weapon class would
also be present in its subclasses
any given sword or club would also want
access to the methods that allow them to
deal damage
as well as the attributes that detail
how much and what type of damage they
deal
the class hierarchy does not tend to be
so small however
as in most cases there are many more
layers than just one superclass and a
couple of subclasses
the weapon class may be a subclass to a
broader items class
which could contain many other
subclasses with subclasses of their own
additionally you may include a wider
variety of weapons than just swords and
clubs
as well as multiple types of swords that
would require different behaviors and
thus their own subclasses
when you are writing object-oriented
code
many of the classes you create will fit
somewhere in the broader class hierarchy
which acts as a web of classes with
different relationships to one another
the next important topic to cover in
terms of inheritance is the access
modifiers that change which classes
access which attributes methods or even
classes as a whole
there are three main access modifiers
that we will be discussing
public
private
and protected
let's begin with the public modifier
public is probably the most simple of
the modifiers
a public member or class can be accessed
from anywhere
this includes any superclasses
subclasses or anywhere else in the
program
this is very useful when you need to
have access from a wide variety of
places in your program
to better understand this modifier and
those to come
look to the example class hierarchy on
screen that represents different foods
for each example the member in question
will be defined in the fruit class
green classes have access and red
classes do not
as you can see
a public member being defined in this
class or anywhere else can be accessed
from anywhere in your program
next we have the private modifier
private members can only be accessed
from within the same class that the
member is defined
this is best to use if you do not need
this information accessed from anywhere
else in the program
additionally
this allows you to create other private
members of the same name in separate
classes which will not conflict with one
another due to their private access
modifier
as you can see on the example class
hierarchy
a private member defined in the fruit
class
can only be accessed inside the fruit
we then have the protected modifier
a protected variable can be accessed
from within the class it is defined
as well as any subclasses of that class
essentially
protected variables are private to the
class hierarchy that they are defined in
this can be seen in the example class
hierarchy right now
in this final section we will be
covering the final of the four main
principles
polymorphism
polymorphism describes methods that are
able to take on many forms
there are two types of polymorphism
the first one is what is called dynamic
polymorphism
dynamic polymorphism occurs during run
time when the program is being executed
this describes when a method signature
is present in both a subclass and a
superclass
the methods share the same parameters
but have separate implementation
in this case
the subclasses implementation of the
method overrides the superclasses
let's go over an example
let's say you are writing a program to
represent many different types of cars
in a class hierarchy
at the top of the hierarchy you may have
the generic car class
you then may create a sports car class
as a subclass of the car class
you then may create a dot drive method
in both of the classes
in each of the classes the dot drive
function will take a double representing
the number of miles you would like the
car to drive
and the car's gas attribute will be
decreased by the pertinent amount
in the car class
the dot drive function may cause the
car's gas to decrease by 0.04 gallons
per mile
whereas the sports car class
may instead have its gas decreased by
0.02 gallons per mile it drives
if you create an instance of a sports
car called my sports car
the sports car implementation of the dot
drive method will override the generic
car version of the dot drive method
therefore
my sportscar.drive will decrease my
sports car's gas attribute
by 0.02 gallons per mile
however
were you to create an instance of the
car class called my car
my car.drive would instead decrease my
car's gas
by 0.04 gallons per mile
this is an example of dynamic
polymorphism as the implementation of a
method signature can change depending on
which level in the class hierarchy that
it is called
this works this way because the form of
the method that is called is decided
dynamically as the program is run
this idea can be extended across the
class hierarchy in more layers than just
two
you could add more subclasses
representing different types of sports
cars with their own.drive methods with
different implementations
and creating an instance of each of
these subclasses
would use their own implementation of
the dot drive method one call
the main benefit of dynamic polymorphism
is that it allows you to write methods
in the superclass without having to
include ifs and outshifts to account for
exactly which subclass is being used
when the method is called
the second type of polymorphism is
static polymorphism
static polymorphism occurs during
compile time
rather than run time
this refers to when multiple methods
with the same name
are defined in the same class
in this case the methods are
differentiated by their arguments
either they take a different number of
parameters
they take parameters of different types
or they take parameters in a different
order than one
another this is known as method
overloading
despite the names of the methods being
the same they have different method
signatures
due to their differences in the
parameters that they accept
to better understand this let's go back
to the car example
let's say that you are working within
the car class
in this class you are looking to create
three different drive methods
the first drive methods argument accepts
one integer and one string as parameters
say speed and destination
for clarity
we will refer to this one as drive
method one
however keep in mind that its method
name is just drive
for drive method 2
we will set its argument to accept two
integers
for instance distance and speed
finally in drive method 3
we will have it accept a string first
for destination
and then an integer for speed
this differs from drive method 1
in that drive method 1's parameters are
in reverse order compared to drive
method threes
in each of these three example methods
the method signature is different
despite the methods having the same name
therefore the computer is able to tell
the methods apart when the program is
being compiled
for example
where i to call mycar.drive45
work
drive method 1 would be called
as the argument given indicates that
this is the method i would like to call
furthermore my car.drive 1560
would call drive method 2
and my call.drive school 30 would call
drive method three
when implementing method overloading the
different methods tend to have separate
but similar effects
despite drive method one and drive
method three taking the same parameters
it is likely that their implementation
would be different and thus would
achieve separate effects
otherwise there would be no reason to
have both methods
keep in mind that method overloading can
cause trouble if you do not keep
straight which of the methods
implementations you would like to
execute
and what form of the argument is
required to do so
normally if you call a method with too
many parameters or parameters of the
incorrect type
then the program will throw an error and
you will be able to fix the issue
however
if you mistake the methods argument in
such a way that one of the other methods
with the same name is called instead
then you may not even be aware that you
made a
mistake overall
polymorphism simply allows methods to
take on many different forms
it can be very useful in that it allows
methods of the same name to exist both
in the same class
and in different classes
however you must be careful to ensure
that you are calling the correct form of
the method that you want
so your program can function as intended
that does it for polymorphism
and with the end of polymorphism the
final of the four main principles
comes the end of this video on an
introduction to object oriented
programming
if you enjoyed consider liking and
subscribing to null pointer exception
and check out some of our other videos
in which we cover a variety of other
topics that you may find helpful
thanks for watching